what is going on guys welcome back to
another Android application development
video in Android Studio in this video we
are going to create a chat GPT generate
image application so from this
application we will generate any image
with the help of open AI by sending just
a text so I will show you the example so
let's say tiger with iPhone
click on generate
so as you can see tiger is in with
iPhone you can generate any of the image
like
moon with eyes
and ear
so as you can see it can generate
anything so let's build this application
from start
let's get started with new project click
on new project
empty activity
and give the name
easy image generator
select language as Java minimum SDK as
API 23 click on finish
our project is loaded first we will go
to manifest and add the internet usage
permission so go to manifest and usage
permission
internet
close the Manifest go to Activity
main.xml Click on split
say hello to this hello world and delete
it make this constant layout as a
relative layout
first we will Design the screen and we
will add the implementation we will make
the simple design we don't want to make
a complex UI so let's get started
let's create a text view first
wrap content wrap content
text will be
generate
image now
text size will be 30 SP and I will
Center it in horizontal true ID I will
give Edge text view for now below this
will make a linear layout where we will
add one edit text one button one
progress bar and one image view so let's
add linear layout
virtually match parent height will be
wrap content and inside that I will give
orientation as vertical so that we will
add vertically let's create a edit text
first edit text with fully match parent
height will be wrap content I will give
the hint right here
so you can see over here I will Center
this linear layout so Center vertical
will be true
and gravity also Center so this is our
edit text we'll give the padding about
12 DP and we'll give the margin vertical
20 DB below this let's create a button
so I will use material button with fully
match parent height will be about 60 DP
here is the button
text will be generate padding will be 12
ldp ID we will give as
generate
BTN now I need one progress bar so that
we can show the progress and one image
view to show the image so let's add
progress bar
width will be match parent height will
be 60 DB ID will be progress
circular
and tint I will give indeterminate tint
as a primary color so design default
color primary so that color will be same
so now below this I will make an image
view to show the image
so image view width will be about 256 DP
height will be 256 DB ID will be image
View
I'll give some margin top 40 DP and I
will give some color for now like black
we can change the color from here let's
say custom some gray color
okay and I will give the margin on this
relative layout about 20 DB
from every side so our application
designing is completed let's run it and
test it how it is looking
our application is looking good we have
to change this primary color we have to
remove this action bar and we have to
remove this visibility of this progress
bar
so first thing progress bar visibility
will be gone
and let's go to resource
you know values themes themes.xml let's
make it no action bar
on both of
no X and Bar
so
now X and bar will be removed now let's
change the primary color so this is our
primary color
I will change this purple 200 to
a red one
this one also 500 to 600 red one
and this one 700 red
let's run it and see how it is looking
so it is looking better now so we have
removed the action bar so now let's
implement the code in mainactivity.java
so let's go to main activity
here let's initialize all those views we
we have added text input text we can
give
material button we generate button
progress bar progress bar
image View
image view now provide the ID input text
equals to find view by IDR dot ID dot we
have not given the ID for edit text
let's go and give the ID over here
input text let's get back to this and
input text
generate button
ID dot generate button
progress bar
I read out progress
so we have not given the ID for Progress
bar also but we have given progress
circular
let's change it to progress
bar
and over here r dot ID dot progress
which is visible now image View
dot ID dot image View
now on click of generate button we'll
get the text so here generate button dot
set on click listener I will use the
Lambda expression
so on click of this what we will do we
will get the text
equals to input text Dot get text Dot
two string dot trim
so we'll get that text in our text
string
let's check if text Dot is empty
if it is empty we can set the error so
input text Dot set error can't be empty
we'll return from here if it is not
empty we'll call the API we'll pass the
text
we have not created this method we will
create this method over here called API
which will take the string text
will make it
avoid so here we will do the API call
now let's run the application and check
how it is working till now
if I write if I don't write anything and
click on generate it is showing error
that is text can't be empty if I write
something it will go to this call Api
method so our app is working now we will
add the library to call the API Library
you can use volley library or okay HTTP
in this video I am using Okay HTTP now
go to Google
search for Okay HTTP Android
go to this link
and you can read the documentation copy
this implementation line from here
copy this one
go to your project in build.gradle
module file
over here
paste that so we have added okay HTTP
Library click on sync now
go to main activity you can check the
documentation over here how to call the
API so I will copy these two lines first
we need this post to a server so I will
copy this
here we can paste it
and input all this
now we have to call the Post method so I
will not copy it from here I will write
my own so let's go to call Api method
and first create a request body so
request body will be our Json object so
Json object
Json body I will give the name
and I will put something in this Json
body so what to put we have to check the
API first so which API we are calling so
we have to call some API to generate the
image from our text so we are using open
AI API so so go to Google and search for
open AI API
go to this site
here you can see explore the API option
click on get started
if you have already created the account
you can log in or if you have not
created the account you can create your
account I have already created so I will
login
so from here you can go to API reference
over here
click on images over here
you can see this URL so we need this URL
and this request body so in request body
we need prompt and size response format
and user so here we will be using prompt
and size so let's go to our project here
Json body dot put
we will add prompt The Prompt will be
our text
Json body dot put
we'll add size size will be
256 x 256.
so here it will give error because you
have to add it inside try catch so try
put it inside try
catch
exception e will print the exception
that's it so we have defined the Json
body from this we will make the request
body so request body
request body equals to
request body dot create Json body dot
two string second thing you need is
this media type that is our Json so just
pass that Json over here
that's it we have now request body now
from this we have to make a request so
that we can call the API so request
request equals to
new request we will make a builder
pattern Builder
dot URL what is the URL you can go to
open AI
and copy the URL from here this is the
URL
dot we need header also I will put
header just now
we need post as body request body
and we will build so we need header what
is the header header is the API key that
is provided by the open AI so to
generate the API key you have to go over
here
you can see view API Keys click on that
and here create a new secret key so
click on that
copy this API key because once you close
this you will not get again so I have
copied it go back to the project in
header and write as authorization and
second parameter value will be
Bearer
space paste that so we have to write b
error one space and the API key that's
it we have also added the header now we
just have to call the API so to call the
API we have client dot new call we have
to pass the request dot in queue so that
we will get the Callback new callback
click on enter
so we have two method over here on
failure and on response on failure we
will just show the message toast dot
make text
we will say
failed to generate
image
length will be long dot show
that's it on failure we have to just
show the message so if we got the
response what we will do is let's log
the refs once so log
dot i response
it will be response dot body dot string
so let's see what response comes so we
have written the call Api method where
we have added URL and the header
correctly now we are calling the API
Let's test what we will get as a
response so run it
I will open the logcat
and let's write test
click on generate
so as you can see we have some response
that is response we have the Json object
where we have one is created one is data
and inside data we have Json array where
we have URL let's copy this URL and open
in browser
so as you can see we have test image so
our image is being generated now let's
get this URL from this Json object and
put it in an image view so for that
what I will do first is I will convert
this body to a Json object
Json object equals to new Json object
response dot body dot string I have to
put it in try catch
so
in catch exception e
e dot print
so once I get the Json object what I
will do I will put it in image URL so
image URL equals to from Json object
first I will get Json array since we
have the Json array of object that is
data
and inside that Json array we can see in
lock cat we have first element that is
this object so this is the Json object
inside data so dot get Json object index
will be 0 first element and we will get
this string so get string
the name is URL
in this way we will get this image URL
inside this image URL string now we have
to load this image URL in our image view
that's it so we will write load image
image URL so you have to create the
method for loading the image so avoid
load image it will take the URL
load image so here we will load the
image so loading the image from URL to
the image view we need some Library so
we have Glide Library we have Picasso
Library I will use the Picasso Library
go to Google search for Picasso Library
Android
go to this website and you can copy the
dependency so from here copy this
go to build at Gradle
paste it over here
click on sync now
now we can use this Library
to load the image we will use because so
dot get
so we have Picasso dot get Dot
load URL
into Target will be our image View
that's it it will load the URL to our
image view now this load image method we
are calling from callback function so we
have to do it in UI thread so run on UI
thread
we need one method
we will use Lambda
so inside this run on UI thread I will
cut this and paste it so once we call
from this callback method we will run an
UI thread so let's run it and test it it
is working or not
so first we will write test generate
so as you can see the image is generated
and test written over here
in this way I can write cat with the
laptop
let's click on generate
so image is generated so as you can see
when I click on generate button it is
taking some time to call the API and
load the image so I will use that
progress bar to show the progress so we
have this progress bar over here but
when we call the API progress bar should
be visible and when we get the response
it should be invisible so let's make a
method for that
void set in progress
we'll take a Boolean value in progress
so if in progress we can make a progress
bar dot set visibility visible
and generate button we will set it as
gone
same way if it is not in progress we
will do opposite of it
progress bar will be gone
generate button will be visible
so when we call the API we should make
it visible so set in progress will be
true
and when we get the response it will be
set in progress will be false so in the
same way we are calling it from callback
method so we have to put it on run on UI
thread
I will cut this out and paste it over
here so our progress bar should also be
visible let's run it
let's generate some tiger
eating grass with
phone on hand
click on generate progress bar is
visible
now you can say tiger is eating grass
and we have phone on hand so in this way
you can generate anything from here so
let's write something
hers
watching movie in Moon with rabbit
let's generate it
so in this way you can make your app
which will generate any image for you
in this way you can generate any image
from your application we are using open
AI API so you can check usage over here
from billing
or from usage you can check your usage
we have 18 as free credit I have used
only 0.83 so if you enjoyed this video
please hit the like button if you have
any doubts and queries please comment
below I will reply for you don't forget
to hit the Subscribe button before going
see you in the next video bye bye
[Music]